<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <atom:link href="https://tsoukaladelis.xyz/html/Essays/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        <title>Chris Tsoukaladelis Essays</title>
        <link>https://tsoukaladelis.xyz/html/Essays/</link>
        <description>Essays on things I find interesting</description>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <item>
            <title>Neo-Luddism in the era of AI</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 13 Dec 2023 4:50:00 EST</pubDate>
            <link>https://tsoukaladelis.xyz/html/Essays/0x0001.html</link>
            <guid>https://tsoukaladelis.xyz/html/Essays/0001</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[
            <p>
            I would like to open this essay by saying that I am very strongly against
            Neo-Luddism. I find it to be mostly an exercise in futility - can you
            really halt a movement that takes a life of its own once it really gets
            going? Betteridge's law of headlines holds true here as well, of course.
            And so we find ourselves in a time of truly neck-breaking technological
            changes, for which the current systems of power (Adam Curtis would be
            proud) are usually too slow to react to. 
            </p>
            <p>
            In most arguments, I tend to attempt and view both sides as best I can, to
            varying effect - on subjects pertaining to technology the effect is really
            diminished. I grew up with a very specific ideal of what technology should 
            be, so I find it difficult to reconcile when technological progress races 
            off to the near-opposite direction. Regardless.
            </p>
            <p>
            On the positives, there's of course the billions of hours of soul-crushing
            work that are performed on a yearly basis that AI could really streamline.
            Entire lives spent in front of excel spreadsheets, tax documents, you name
            it. I personally believe strongly that every person has a calling to them,
            and I have a suspicion that sitting in front of a computer placing numbers in
            different cells is not it, for most.
            </p>
            <p>
            Then you have self-driving cars. A true technological feat, the
            door is now open for people to get blackout drunk and still get home safe.
            Considering automobile accidents are one of the leading causes of premature 
            death worldwide, this is a cause for celebration. At this point - and
            potentially sooner for some - a voice in the back of your head is probably
            telling you "yes, sure Chris, however".
            </p>
            <p>
            However, what about the fact that cars are now software-controlled? What
            about the fact that they can be hacked? What about the fact that this is a
            technology that belongs almost solely to Tesla? What about all the people
            that AI will put out of a job when there's no more numbers to put in cells?
            I don't consider these to be the <strong>true</strong> problems of AI. I
            find them to be immediate problems needing solutions, of course, but they
            are reactionary more than anything else. 
            </p>
            <p>
            I would like to interject in my own thought process here for a second and
            state the obvious - AI has been around for decades, and what is now being
            popularized are advances in specific subfields (mostly generative AI, in
            the case of chatGPT, the main method of interacting with the AI overlords by
            everyday people). For sensationalist as well as purely aesthetic reasons, I
            talk about "AI" here focusing on the subject as one would view it from a
            philosophical perspective. A black box that takes in input and produces
            output akin to that of an intelligent being.
            </p>
            <p>
            With that out of the way, let us return our focus to problems AI creates in
            the <i>now</i>. I find them to be no different than the "problems" created
            by the automobile industry, or fridges, or the industrial revolution. And
            again, you will say;  but Chris, the industrial revolution and its
            consequences- and I will agree, partly. It has not all been a simple, 
            temporal, reactionary problem that can simply be solved with the creation of new
            jobs as humanity evolves. And this takes me to my next point.
            </p>
            <p>
            The <strong>real</strong> problems of AI, are philosophical in nature, in
            my view. AI is created in the image of its creators, and this primordial
            pool is not a fun one to look at, from the get-go. This has to do with how
            AI operates - there is an input, as mentioned, which is then moved to a
            black box, and then there is an output. And humans don't understand
            the black box part now, and it is likely that as AI gets more and more
            complex that humans will <strong>never</strong> understand the black box
            part. So really, you have an input and an output, take it or leave it.
            </p>
            <p>
            But let us assume that for better or for worse the mathematics behind the
            black box part is sound (this is not an easy assumption to make, and
            thousands of statisticians spun in their graves as you read that sentence).
            Surely one can make the argument now that the output is good - in a perfect
            world perhaps. But we live in a deeply imperfect world, with millenia of
            deep-seated hatreds, injustices and atrocities. There is not enough trolley
            problem images in the world to even begin to describe how difficult it
            would be to "level the playing field" for an AI, when we cannot even do the
            same as humans. 
            </p>
            <p>
            To visualize this problem for someone less tech-savvy, consider this very
            rough sketch of an example, meant simply to outline the problem. Let's
            assume you come from a poor family, and are seeking a loan from your local 
            community bank. Your ancestors haven't had the opportunity to perform money
            management before, as in prior states of government it was a privilege
            reserved for the already wealthy. The times have changed however, and 
            you, vowed to make the most of your newfound freedom of choice. You now go to the
            bank, and their Frankenstein's version of Clippy takes in your details and
            will then tell you if you are eligible for a loan (let's assume for the
            sake of brevity that there is no risk calculations at play). The AI now
            sees that no one you are related to has ever taken out a loan before.
            Immediately, you would start off with a disadvantage. 
            </p>
            <p>
            One does not need much imagination to see the above play out, as it
            effectively already is the way the system works. The only difference is
            there are humans that are more-or-less able to understand the system and
            can slightly lean on the scales a bit to make it fairer. However, as AI
            progresses and is able to take more and more of this workload, the problems
            will no doubt start to accumulate and create massive societal rifts. This
            is mostly fact, as far as I am concerned.
            </p> 
            <p>
            The "solution" to the above, however, is also very problematic. Governments
            all around the world will attempt to put their finger on the scale not as
            outside observers, as your random bank clerk might, but as part of the
            system, effectively building it in. Even assuming no corruption as is
            usually encountered during any bureaucratic process and system of power, it
            would be impossible to predict what the outcome of such a built-in
            counterweight would be, when one does not understand the black box to begin
            with, and what alteration of the input leads to a "better" output. 
            </p>
            <p>
            Which kind of hints to my main struggle with AI, which I saved for last. I
            could go on forever, of course, but I will no doubt return to this topic
            someday, and I do not really like to theorize ad nauseum. So far, humans
            have progressed technologically at a given pace, but now they are putting
            more and more faith in a system which they do not (for the most part)
            understand, that is very much beholden to a board of directors and has to
            turn a profit. No doubt, people are already putting more blind faith into 
            it than they should. It can summarize a page for you, it can translate 
            words for you, it can book "the cheapest" plane tickets for you, once 
            given your financial information. 
            </p>
            <p>
            It is very difficult for me to come to a conclusion here, both on the
            question of AI as well as thematically on this essay, but I keep returning to a
            quote from the film Pulse by Kiyoshi Kurosawa; <q>No matter how simple the 
            device, once the system's complete, it'll function all on its own and become 
            permanent</q>. This system has become permanent, and we need to learn to
            live with it, to understand its shortcomings and how our own human nature
            can work against us. It is going to be a difficult road ahead.
            </p>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Humble Beginnings</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2023 6:20:00 EST</pubDate>
            <link>https://tsoukaladelis.xyz/html/Essays/0x0000.html</link>
            <guid>https://tsoukaladelis.xyz/html/Essays/0000</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[
    <p>
        I was never good at writing. Some say it takes a lot of reading, but 
        I have little faith in that reasoning. If reading meant you could write, 
        I'd be a movie director by now. To others, it is simply a matter of 
        habit. If that is the case, then perhaps this text will serve as a testament 
        to how bad I once was, one day. Regardless, one has to begin from somewhere.
    </p> 
    <p>
        I am currently finishing the second year of my PhD. This, too, is a
        matter of taking things one step at a time, as my parents used to say.
        My 6 year old self was most likely annoyed that he had to go to school,
        dreading the 9 months of imprisonment ahead of him. Surely, I would have
        thrown a tantrum had anyone told me I'd be in and out of classrooms for
        the next 20-some years.
    </p>
    <p>
        Surely, everyone must have read and heard of this hundreds of times:
        Take things one step at a time. Don't lose track of your goals. Carpe
        diem. An entire book's worth of motivational quotes, many times
        contradicting one another, stemming from millenia of human experience,
        mostly made as blanket statements on the daily. There is naturally truth 
        to all of them; after all they survived a lengthy process of linguistic
        darwinism. 
    </p>
    <p> 
        There is allegedly a Churchill quote about how inspirational
        quotes kept him motivated, but naturally searching for it bombards you
        with inspirational quotes by Churchill himself. If that quote did
        indeed exist, I wonder if it was a matter of populism, or his sincere
        thinking. History fascinates me, and I'd love to write about it more
        one day. 
    </p>
    <p>
        Writing is, for me, also a hobby, albeit a very new one. I don't find
        it "meditative" or anything like that, if anything I find it rather
        stressful. Not necessarily because of what you might think about my
        (mostly amateur) essays to follow, but because I myself might not like
        them. I have decided to not change things that I have already written
        (a practice that ironically ties in with my research), so what I write 
        here will be here to stay, regardless of what I myself think about it
        ten or twenty years down the line. 
    </p>
    <p>
        There's all sorts of subjects I want to write about, from technology
        (of course) to linguistics, to history, to film. I am very torn about
        the idea of using current events as a jump-off point to dive into
        larger topics. Their temporal nature might work to my detriment, but
        then again this blog is a product of its time. Actually, the word blog
        itself is already antiquated, as far as I know. Regardless, I hope you
        enjoy these posts and join me in this journey.
</p>]]></description>
            </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
